Hagar's thank you very much for coming with me so far in the.
Congratulations for completing this course.
This is the last thing which you have to do as a project manager.
And this is the last video as part of the knowledge areas of schools.
I will continue to update this course with the bonus sections.
But in terms of pinball last process group which you need to study basically when you start a project
it goes through a cycle.
First you initiate the project then you plan the project followed by executing the project.
Then you monitor and control the project and finally close the project for initiating.
We went through two processes which were for product charter and stakeholders.
A lot of activities for planning executing and monitoring and controlling the project.
So all those processes from all those knowledge areas in closing the project are a phase and we need
to perform certain activities.
It's not just that you deliver the product or project deliverables and your work is done.
And remember when I say closing the project I mean closing the project which is the new project or the
phase of the project.
So if we are losing out this phase we need to follow the same protocols same standards.
So in this process we basically finalize all the activities and we are done and we will formally close
the project.
We could have some kind of meetings as go no go where they decide if they want to accept the delivery
or not.
If things are not going well there are a lot of open defects.
All the stakeholders can even decide to not accept the project.
It's not very common but not very very old so technically it is not part of closing process group but
it's very activity which happens around that stage.
So it's very important for you to know that it happens at the same time when you are doing the closing
process group activities for project delivery you can have a separate meeting at the time of delivery
where everybody provides the sign off usually when the deployment happens and you will have business
stakeholders who will formally provide to sign off in the form of e-mails.
So they will test things.
They will run you know quick check out.
They will see that everything is working.
Project manager will make sure that all the deliverables will include not only the actual product work
like a software a house or a road but also on the documents.
If there are any legal contracts they should be closed.
And if we are now closing the project earlier than expected then we are doing that.
And if any formality around that should be completed and that has to be a checklist.
And most organizations will have some kind of checklist where they will perform that all the deliverables
are there all the activities are closed.
What is going on.
Nobody can charge their.
After the project is closed.
And the best way to do that is to close all the WB task cords which are there in the time sheet.
Now of course you're going to still have two task assigned to the project task like in any follow up
task any volunteer task.
But most of the development tasks should be closed when you are going to deliver the project.
Usually this process can only happen once.
As you can expect So whether we are closing the fees or the project it has to happen only once.
If this is the second and we are doing that then something went wrong.
So documents like exemption log basis office timber issue Love lesson learned registers they all are
updated with relevant information.
Most of the time they will be part of deliverables.
And so we need to deliver them to the client.
And once you finish all that is based on your checklist or whatever processes your company follow for
closing the project.
You have done a great job you should congratulate yourself not only on completing the project.
So now you have completed the schools so this in this video if you have any and section if you have
any question any doubt please.
You can use the form which I have mentioned earlier or reach out to me through e-mails to my website
hobe discourse has been useful to you.
You can use the information here to play in your daily job.
And also you'll get many scenario based questions in PMP Exam so you can use this information which
you have learned here.
Just remember the key items like these are cycled for Project initiation.
Everything has to be planned.
Everything has to be monitored and controlled.
There are Bistline and we can not avoid them.
So use your learning and think like a project manager.
There are certain things that you need to remember like in ports.
Our ports and techniques I have a test aspect chute which contains an somebody of all the knowledge
areas and process groups this will help you to quickly check information about all the inboard outboards
tools and techniques mentioned in the bin Bob.
But if you receive a scenario based question where you're not sure about the answer then go for the
most logical option based on your understanding of the project management fundamentals.
Go for the answer which you think should be done in a normal board in a real world.
I wish you luck and I pray for your success.
Please try to finish that quizzes and assignment in discourse that will really help you to understand
the concept of the project management practices and that will help you with your PMP preparation also.
Thank you.